上一次我們提過出埃及這件事蹟
是大約在公元前1500至1200年之間發生
當時的世界都是面臨史無前例的動盪
近東有很多人正在遷徙 正在移居
想找一個安居之所
我們舉個例子就是海人Sea Peoples
其中一組人就是菲利士人Philistines
在大歷史的圖畫中 以色列人是其中一群正在遷徙
他們在埃及被欺壓了多年
他們離開時前無去路 後有追兵
但有特別的地方是他們發現上帝親自帶領他們
對於今天你和我面對社會政局的不穩
有一種被迫的感覺流散在世界不同的地方
都同樣面對很多的改變 身份的改變 很多未知之數
這樣看出埃及這個故事 似乎對我們來說非常切身
但當我們看出埃及這個技術的時候
我們一定要梳理一下歷史的問題
為什麼呢 因為在舊約聖經裏面
經常提到出埃及這件歷史事蹟
可以這樣說 在舊約歷史當中
出埃及這件事就有如新約的耶穌基督從死裏復活
歷史性都是這麼重要的
但在過去幾十年 越來越多人質疑
為什麼沒有證據證明出埃及這件事件
或者可能出埃及會是很後期虛構的故事
我記得好幾年前在一個香港的電台上受過訪問
主持人問了一個問題 也是很有道理的
他說出埃及這麼大件事 總會有一點點線索吧
居然一點線索都沒有 有些道理我們必須承認
暫時到現在都沒有直接的歷史證明
但是我們這樣說也好 我們都需要留意幾件事
第一 證據的不存在不一定等於不存在的證據
這個你動高床板就要想一想
The absence of evidence is not the evidence of absence
因為很多歷史的事蹟
包括聖經或者聖經以外的歷史事蹟
都未必會找到考古的證據
我們不能夠踏時光機回去以前
將歷史放在化驗室裏面去證明多一次
何況你想想當時的背景
埃及帝國是獨裁的政權
他們不會將失敗的事蹟寫下來
第二件事我們需要留意的
就是當我們想起考古證據的時候
我們對考古證據的要求一定要實際
假設以色列人出埃及的話
你想想他們會帶著什麼
他們好像難民一樣離開埃及
我不知道你有沒有做過服務難民的工作
我記得有一次我參與一個難民服務的工作
去到機場接一家六口從剛果難民營來的難民
六個人他們入境下機的時候
每個人你想想他們帶著什麼
他們只是帶著一個小的膠袋
就是這麼多
所以你再想一想
作為難民甚至作為平民百姓也好
過了一百年之後
你看看我們這一班平民百姓的人
都一定是蕭姓匿跡的
就是說在考古歷史裡面是見不到我們的
所以為什麼有這麼多皇帝想見皇陵
大墳墓有兵馬俑金字塔等等
因為他們想留芳百世
所以沒有考古證據不代表你不存在
再有一點需要留意的
就是如果你真的按照聖經所說
以色列人在埃及住了好幾代
如果他們出埃及的時候
你想想他們帶著什麼實物出來
衣服啊瓷器啊日用品等等
但是這些全部的東西
都必定是埃及製造的
Made in Egypt
所以他們到曠野就算留下這些實物
我們找到我們只會當是有一班人
埃及人他們經過留下過在這裡
舉個很簡單的例子
我的子女都是在美國出生長大的
我看遍他們擁有的實物裡面
我真的找不到哪一樣可以直接表明他們是華裔第二代
除了他們現在在生的樣子是像亞裔的人
但是他們說的想的都是美國本土化的
所以我想如果他們真的化了灰的話
他們的實物是跟其他白人啊黑人啊
這裡的美國人是沒有任何分別的
所以我們對這個考古的證據的要求
是需要實際一點的
我們不會找到一塊石上面寫著
摩西到此一遊
你說沒有直接的歷史考古的證據
那是不是就這樣算了
但其實也不是的
在歷史的探索裡面我們要多問一個問題
就是有沒有一些間接性的
情況性的背景的旁證
即是circumstantial background的evidence
如果這樣問的時候可能真的有
因為如果出埃及記真是後期虛構著作
即是到波斯時代公元前500年的時候才寫
他的描述裡面一定是會用一些後期的字眼
但如果出埃及記真是寫當時歷史的事跡
他的描述一定是配合當時的語言
當時的環境
如果是這樣的話
歷史可靠性就會高很多
那你問前前後後又說早期又後期的描述
好像很難明白很抽象
其實一點都不難明白
我播以下一個短片
你就知道有什麼問題了
是 皇上
父皇 濟英的大軍要二十天才去到白利浦
但每日的軍餉二成二十萬兩
我們的國庫已經所剩無幾
朕暫時不能給那麼多了
惟今之計
只要交了十五、十六和十七這三萬的軍餉
其他的再慢慢想辦法
皇上 讓奴婢替你換個盆熱水
周兄弟 同朕再查一下
看各地各省還有沒有人欠稅
朕要將這些稅項一次過追回來
臣遵旨
明眼人一看就明白了
因為朕是不會用check這個字的
看上去好像很好笑
但其實這裡點出了一樣東西
就是如何鑒定一個歷史文件可靠性的原則
官方說出埃及記
如果歷史可靠的話
那裏面的描述一定是吻合公元前
一千五百至一千年之間
那時候是New Kingdom Period
是古埃及帝國的新王國時期
那時候是埃及最後輝煌的時期
看看當時埃及的歷史文件
用什麼字眼
描述什麼地理
然後再去比對一下
出埃及記我們就知道它的歷史可靠性
舉幾個例子
出埃及記一章第十一節
於是埃及人派督公管轄他們
就是以色列人
加重他們的負擔和害他們
他們為法老建造兩座積火城
就是彼東和蘭室
使他們因做苦工覺得命苦
無論和禮、做磚、做田間各樣的工
在一切的工上都嚴嚴待他們
這裏細緻的描述
做磚、和禮和一切的工
我帶你去一個埃及的墓穴
叫做Tomb of Reck-Marie
雷克米爾墓穴
這個人在公元前十五世紀
即是一千四百多年的時候
在埃及做大官
在他的墓穴裏面有很多壁畫
裏面描述很多奴隸
包括戰俘
他們在田間做很多事
這個和出埃及記的描述是非常吻合的
你看到這個圖畫這一部分
有人在池裏拿水上來
有些奴隸在和禮
有些在做磚
包括在田間裏面各樣的工作
細緻地去看的時候
那些埃及的督工是拿著木棒來管轄他們
另一方面我們可以看地理
一章第十一節
兩座的積貨城
叫彼東和蘭室
蘭室是法老的名字
有一個很出名的法老王
叫蘭室二世或蘭室大帝
Ramesses II
蘭室城真是存在的
Ramesses或Ramesses
在舊約聖經裏面只提過五次
都是在摩西五經裏面提過的
而我們知道蘭室城
Pyramus的城市在埃及的文獻裏面出現過
亦都是蘭室二世這個法老所建的京都
說起蘭室二世的法老
他就很出名
因為很多人都認為
這個很可能是出埃及的法老
但說到考古
蘭室城我們知道的
只是有二百年的歷史
由公元前1270至1070年之間
為什麼最後會被荒廢呢?
因為當時利羅河在三角洲的平地經常會改道
利羅河對埃及人來說
是很重要的
等於今天的高速公路
交通、貿易、軍事的樞紐都是靠這條河
所以這條河改道
城市在兩百年之後就被荒廢了
那些埃及人就很懂得復原
他們就把本身在蘭室城裏面的石碑
有蘭室二世的名字的石碑
搬到北面十二英里
建另外一個城鎮
那個城鎮叫做索安
或者希臘文是丹尼斯
說起索安城或者丹尼斯
如果你記得或者你接觸過
1981年的時候
有一套電影叫做《奪寶奇兵》
In the End of Jones' Waders of the Lost Ark
裏面是提過丹尼斯這個古城
電影裏面的橋段就是說二次大戰的時候
德國納粹黨就要叫法國的考古學家
去丹尼斯索安這個地方找藥櫃
你看看以下這個短短兩三分鐘的片段
你告訴我有什麼是真有什麼是虛構
Yes, I did.
Dr. Jones, you must understand
that this is all strictly confidential.
I understand.
Yesterday afternoon, our European sections
intercepted a German communique
that was sent from Cairo to Berlin.
You see, over the last two years,
the Nazis have had teams of archaeologists
running around the world
looking for all kinds of religious artifacts.
Hitler's a nut on the subject.
He's crazy.
He's obsessed with the occult.
And right now, apparently,
there's some kind of German archaeological dig
going on in the desert outside of Cairo.
Now, we've got some information here,
but we can't make anything out of it,
and maybe you can.
Tannis Development Proceeding
Acquire Headpiece Staff of Ra Abner Ravenwood, US.
Nazis have discovered Tannis.
What does that mean to you, Tannis?
The city of Tannis
is one of the possible resting places
of the Lost Ark.
The Lost Ark?
Yeah, the Ark of the Covenant,
the chest the Hebrews used to carry around
the Ten Commandments.
What do you mean "Ten Commandments"?
You're talking about the Ten Commandments?
Yes, the actual Ten Commandments,
the original stone tablets
that Moses brought down out of Mount Herob
and smashed, if you believe in that sort of thing.
Any of you guys ever go to Sunday school?
Well, I...
No, look.
The Hebrews took the broken pieces
and put them in the Ark,
when they settled in Canaan.
They put the Ark in a place
called the Temple of Solomon.
In Jerusalem?
Where it stayed for many years
until all of a sudden, whoosh, it's gone.
Where?
Well, nobody knows where or when.
However, an Egyptian pharaoh...
Shishak.
Yes, invaded the city of Jerusalem
around about 980 B.C.
and he may have taken the Ark
back to the city of Tannis
and hidden it in a secret chamber
called the Well of Souls.
Secret chamber?
However, about a year after
the pharaoh had returned to Egypt,
the city of Tannis was consumed
by the desert in a sandstorm
which lasted a whole year,
wiped clean by the wrath of God.
Now, what does this Ark look like?
I...
There's a picture of it right here.
That's it.
Good God!
Yes, that's just what the Hebrews thought.
Now, what's that supposed to be
coming out of there?
Lightning.
Fire.
Power of God or something.
You can't understand Hitler's interest in it.
Oh, yes.
The Bible speaks of the Ark leveling mountains
and laying waste to entire regions.
An army which carries the Ark before it
is invincible.
So, what's the truth?
If you've been to Sunday School,
you'll know that there's the Ark.
Also, you should know that
in 900 B.C.,
there was a pharaoh named Shishak.
He really attacked Jerusalem
and took away the treasures
of the temple and the palace.
This is explained in the 14th chapter of the Book of Kings.
The Ark's whereabouts
is another big topic.
We won't talk about it today.
No matter what,
when it comes to Tennis,
Denis, Soin and Zouan,
these cities,
it's true that since 1928,
the French archaeologists
started to excavate.
They've been doing it for years.
In the first few decades,
the French archaeologists
thought that Soin and Zouan,
Tennis,
were the solid rocks in the Aegean.
That's where they found the treasures
and the stones.
But they found out later that it was wrong.
Soin and Tennis
are an ancient city of 1,000 years.
But they were built in 1070.
So it's a later city.
The later books of the Bible
also mention Soin and Tennis.
In the 78th and 12th chapters of the Book of Psalms,
it says that God in the fields of Soin,
the fields of Soin,
that is,Tennis,
performed a miracle in front of the Lord.
This is very important.
The 78th chapter of the Book of Psalms
is about the plague in the Aegean.
But it says that the place where the plague occurred
was Soin,
not Lansat.
So when the poet wrote this poem,
when he recalled the plague,
he wrote it after 400 to 500 years
after he left Egypt.
At that time, Lansat no longer existed.
So the poet only knew
that the plague occurred in Soin near Lansat.
But when he went back to Egypt,
he saw the details of the geography
and he mentioned Lansat.
This town really existed at that time.
So when it was recorded,
the reliability of history was shown.
You may think that it is very complicated.
In fact,it is not complicated at all.
It is also very simple.
For example,I have lived in Chicago for only 20 years.
I only know the geography of Chicago
for the past 20 years.
You can ask some old Chinese here.
They can tell you that
40 or 50 years ago,
at the same place, the front of the restaurant's name
was named after something.
Today, we can really determine
the location of Lansat.
It is a small village in Alibaba today
called Cantia.
Here we can find
the stone wall of Lansat.
It also has the name of the king.
The stone pillar has the hand of the great man of Lansat.
He is attacking his enemy.
Notice that the Bible always mentions
the hand of the great man is the new shield.
In fact, these are the political phrases
that the French used all the time at that time.
In the ancient city of Lansat,
we can also find a military stable.
There are also many large stones used to tie horses.
It is estimated that this stable
can stop 500 horses
and can stop more than 200 warships.
The ancient city of Lansat is estimated to be as large as 10 square kilometers.
Of course, it is now a field.
But at that time, it was the largest city in the world.
The Egyptian Bible also contains
many special phrases and dictionaries
used by the Egyptian pharaohs at that time.
It does not contain the words of the later Persian period.
On the contrary, the books written in the later period
Ezra and Nehemiah
always contain the words of the Persian period.
We have just spent about 15 minutes
to explain the historical reality of the Egyptian Bible.
In fact, there is no need to doubt.
Now we can take a look at the Egyptian route.
How did God lead the Egyptians out of Egypt?
First, they set out from Lansat.
In chapter 13, verse 17, it is mentioned that
when the pharaoh went there with his people,
the road to Philistine was narrow.
God did not lead them where to go.
Because God said, "I am afraid that the people will turn back to Egypt when they regret the war."
So God led the people to walk on the road to the Red Sea.
Here is a road called the road to Philistine.
This road was also mentioned in the Egyptian documents at that time.
Another name for Egypt is "Way of Horus"
which is the way of Horus in the Egyptian gods.
This is the most convenient way to go from Egypt to Canaan.
It takes only a few days to get to Canaan.
But it is also mentioned in the Bible that
God did not lead the Egyptians on this fastest road.
Why?
Because God said, "I am afraid that the people will turn back to Egypt when they regret the war."
They would rather go back to Egypt on the road.
The archaeology here can help us a lot.
Because on the road to the northwest of the Mediterranean Peninsula,
there were more than a dozen soldiers of the New Roman Empire.
So on this road, there were Egyptian warships to guard.
It was a military stronghold.
So the Bible told us that
if the Egyptians took this shortest road,
they would not be well equipped and would not go to war.
They would definitely regret and go back to Egypt.
The road that God led people on was not necessarily the shortest and fastest.
It was not necessarily our plan.
Sometimes it was even against the common sense.
Another way out of Egypt is the way to the shore in the Bible.
The way to the shore in the Bible.
This is mentioned in Genesis.
Do you remember the story of Hagar?
When she left, she walked on the way to the shore.
So the Israelites started from Lancaster and walked to the southeast.
According to the Bible, they should have gone through the way to the shore to get out of Egypt.
Then they went to Canaan.
But what does the 14th chapter say?
The Lord said, "Suddenly, it was dark."
He said, "You told the Israelites to turn back."
"Turn back" means to go north.
The place where they are now is the Red Sea.
It is actually in front of the Sea of ​​Grass.
Before that, they were afraid that the Israelites would see the signs of war.
So they turned back to Egypt.
So they walked on the way to the shore.
Suddenly, the Lord called them to turn back.
Why?
He called them to turn back when they were at the exit.
What is the Lord's will?
The 14th chapter, chapter 3.
The Lord said, "The Pharaoh must speak."
The Israelites were lost on the ground.
The wilderness trapped them.
Chapter 4.
The Lord said, "I will make Pharaoh's heart harden."
He will chase them.
"Then I will be glorified by Pharaoh and his whole army."
The Egyptians knew that they were in the wilderness.
So the Israelites turned back.
The Lord's will seems to be very complicated.
It is not human reason.
But what is the ultimate purpose?
It is to be glorified by God.
The purpose of the Lord's will is not to exalt us.
It is not that we think we are doing well.
It is to be glorified by God.
We need to learn to trust Him.
As I said at the beginning,
there are many changes in life.
Especially during the pandemic,
we have encountered many unimaginable situations.
We all want to go to an ideal place.
We often say that we don't like the situation.
We don't like the place.
We don't like the context.
So we want to escape.
We think everything is OK.
Of course, this is human reason.
But this story seems to tell us
what is the most important thing in the eyes of God.
The most important thing is not what we think.
Everything is fine.
In Deuteronomy 14,
John said, "This is how Jesus saved the Israelites
from the hands of the Egyptians."
It says that after crossing the Red Sea,
what did the Israelites see?
They saw Jehovah's Witnesses.
What did the Israelites see?
They saw the great things that Jehovah did to the Egyptians.
They knew how to glorify Him.
They knew how to trust God
and His divine magic.
Many times, when we encounter difficulties,
we think that we are leaving this unideal situation.
We are looking for an ideal paradise.
If God really wants to lead us to our ultimate goal,
where there is no disaster, no trouble, no illness,
and we can successfully retire and be happy,
I think God must be our greatest failure.
And the most successful one should be the Egyptian Pharaoh.
Because in the Egyptian Empire,
if you surrender to him,
you will be safe and secure.
So you see, leaving Egypt
does not mean that the Israelites can live in peace for thousands of years.
In fact, after the Israelites left Egypt
and crossed the Red Sea and the Sea of ​​Grass,
there was a trial.
God's purpose was to prepare us
to become a group of people who are faithful to His will.
This is the greatest blessing.
The greatest blessing is not that we have no disaster, no illness,
and no epidemic.
The greatest blessing is that we can become the people of God
and make a covenant with Him.
We have the glory to serve God.
We are now facing different difficulties.
Whether it is an epidemic or a setback in life,
we may need to ask
whether we will still be faithful to God
after going through these difficulties and setbacks.
Whether we will still be faithful to God
or we will be more sincere to God
after going through God's command.
Personally, the Church is the same.
God told us not to waste the difficult path that He has led us on.
No matter how bad the epidemic is,
let the Church go through a new trial.
Let the Church become a Church
that is more in line with His will.
Some scholars have a very interesting point.
They say that the main thing that the God wants to do
is not to take Israelites out of Egypt.
It is not to take the Israelites out of Egypt.
After they left Egypt,
you will find that their hearts still return to Egypt.
They always want to return to the Egyptian Empire
because there is peace and prosperity and prosperity.
The main thing that the God wants to do
when they leave Egypt
is to take Egypt out of the Israelites.
He wants to take Egypt out of the lives of the Israelites
as well as the lives of the Pharaohs,
as well as the lives of the people on earth
who have no disaster or disease.
So that we can truly return to God
and be loyal to Him
and serve Him
and be faithful to Him.
Are we willing to do that?
Let God take away these idols
so that our hearts can truly return to Him.
Let us pray with our hearts.
God, we know that Your path
and Your command
are not what we humans think.
Your ultimate goal
is for our lives to return to You.
Lord, we beg You to take away from our lives
the things we long for, the so-called peace and prosperity
so that the country on earth can give us benefits.
Lord, let our lives truly return to You
and let You be our true Lord.
You continue to lead our lives
and the path ahead of us
no matter what difficulties we are experiencing.
Lord, let us know that the ultimate goal
in Your eyes is not only to have no worries and disasters
but also that our lives can truly return to You.
Continue to train us
and continue to help us and mislead us
so that we can become more useful
and more obedient to Your will.
We pray in this way.
Amen.